A Finding Aid to the Joseph Kaplan Papers, 1915-1977, in the Archives of American Art AAA.kapljose
Archives of American Art
Joseph Kaplan papers
1915-1977
AAA.kapljose
Archives of American Art
4.5 Linear feet
The papers of the painter, photographer, printmaker, and teacher Joseph Kaplan measure 4.5 linear feet and date from 1915-1977. The bulk of the collection consists of printed material, specifically exhibition catalogs. Also found are a large number of photographs taken of and by Kaplan. The papers also include biographical material, correspondence, personal business records, and artwork.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The Joseph Kaplan papers were donated to the Archives of American Art by Marilyn Kearney in 1981.
Separated Materials note
307 nitrate negatives donated to the Archives of American Art with the Joseph Kaplan papers have been removed and are stored in off-site storage. Negatives were duplicated onto safety based film and only select prints were made.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Biographical/Historical note
Joseph Kaplan (1900-1980) was a painter, printmaker, photographer, and teacher who worked primarly in New York and Provincetown. He was most active in the 1940s through the 1950s. Earlier in his career he worked on several WPA Federal Art Projects and Treasury Relief Art Projects.
Joseph Kaplan was born in Minsk, Russia and immigrated with his family to the United States in 1888 at the age of 12. He married Virginia Haber in 1927 and they had no children.
Kaplan studied at the Eductional Alliance Art School and the Art Students League. He went to Provincetown in the mid-twenties as a student of Charles W. Hawthorne with whom he previously studied with at the National Academy of Design. Afterwards he revisited Provincetown intermittently and began to regard the Cape as his summer studio, working there each summer since 1948.
In 1948 he won the first of many gold medals from the Audubon Artists at the National Academy of Design for a marine painting. He was also the first recipient of the John J. Newman Memorial Medal, given by the National Society of Painters in Casein for his Wellfleet, Low Tide. The Shore Studios in Provincetown, the Harry Salpeter Gallery and then Krasner Gallery in New York City represented Kaplan's artwork.
Kaplan predominantly worked in watercolor and oil paint, depicting landscapes and seascapes, and becoming acclaimed as a Colorist and Romanticist. He occasionally painted figures and, as he gained recognition, he traveled extensively in search for subjects. In 1968 Kaplan recieved a grant from Chapelbrook Foundation to live and work for a year in Mexico.
Kaplan's work was included frequently in group exhibitions and he participated in more then 30 major shows in his lifetime. Throughout his career he was a member of many art organizations including Artists League of America, Audubon Artists, Provincetown Art Association, and Cape Cod Art Association. He was continually active in the art life in Provincetown serving as board members, trustees, and judges. He also occasionally taught at art schools including the American Artist School and John Reed Club, and taught a number of private pupils.
Joseph Kaplan died on February 28th, 1980 at the age of 79 in Brewster, Massachusetts.
Scope and Contents note
The papers of the painter, photographer, printmaker, and teacher Joseph Kaplan measure 4.5 linear feet and date from 1915-1977. The bulk of the collection consists of printed material, specifically exhibition catalogs. Also found are a large number of photographs taken of and by Kaplan. The papers also include biographical material, correspondence, personal business records, and artwork.
Biographical material contains a few of Kaplan's personal documents, a number of certificates and medals he recieved during his lifetime, a travel itinerary notebook, and a few hand-written notes.
Kaplan's correspondence is primarily from colleagues, art organizations, galleries, museums, and colleges and universities such as the Corcoran Gallery of Art, National Academy of Design, and Audubon Artists, inc. Also found are letters from friends and colleagues such as Chaim Gross, Adolph Gottlieb, Raphael Soyer, Louis Lozowick, Milton Avery, and Sol Wilson, as well as a large number of letters to his wife Virginia written during his travels.
Personal business records concern Kaplan's art sales, loans, exhibition notifications, and his involvment in the WPA. His artwork is documented in price lists and inventory lists. Some of the material consists of routine transactions not necessarily related to Kaplan's work, including bank records, an address list, and income and expense reports.
Printed Material includes news clippings, exhibition catalogs, exhibition annoucenments, and invitations for Kaplan shows. There are a few published copies and page proofs of Kaplan's commerical artwork.
Artwork includes four Kaplan etchings, three of which are metal plates and one linoleum block. Also included are a few unidentified pen and pencil sketches.
Photographs depict Kaplan, mainly later in his life, and his family. Also found are four of Virginia Kaplan's photograph albums containing images of her and friends from early adulthood. Photographs of Kaplan's friends and colleagues include images of Aya and Eitaro Ishigaki, Chaim Gross, Raphael Soyer, William Gropper, and Joseph De Martini. Also included are photographs taken by Kaplan of New York City, his travels, and artist demonstrations. There are also a large number of photographs of Kaplan's artwork.
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged into 6 series:
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1919-1975 (Box 1, 5, OV 7; 0.3 linear feet)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1929-circa 1975 (Box 1, OV 7; 0.4 linear feet)
Series 3: Personal Business Records, circa 1920-1977 (Box 1; 0.2 linear feet)
Series 4: Printed Material, 1915-1975 (Box 1, 2, 3, OV 7; 2.3 linear feet)
Series 5: Artwork, circa 1940-circa 1960 (Box 3, 5; 2 folders)
Series 6: Photographic Material, 1917-circa 1975 (Box 4, 6, OV 7; 1.3 linear feet)
Audubon Artists (New York, N.Y.); Avery, Milton, 1885-1965; Corcoran Gallery of Art ##naf; DeMartini, Joseph, 1896-1984; Gottlieb, Adolph, 1903-1974; Gropper, William, 1897-; Gross, Chaim, 1904-1991; Ishigaki, Aya; Ishigaki, Eitarō, 1893-1958; Kaplan, Virginia; Lozowick, Louis, 1892-1973; National Academy of Design (U.S.); Soyer, Raphael, 1899-1987; United States.. Public Works Administration.; United States.. Works Progress Administration.; Wilson, Sol; Etchings; Painters -- Massachusetts -- Provincetown; Painters -- New York (State)-- New York; Photographers--Massachusetts--Provincetown; Photographers--New York (State); Photographs; Printmakers -- New York (State) -- New York; Printmakers--Massachusetts--Provincetown; Sketches
- Biographical Material, 1919-1975; Series 1; 0.3 Linear feet Box 1, 5, OV 7
  Scope and Contents note
  Included are various certificates and medals received by Kaplan over the course of his career. Also found are a few teaching files and miscellaneous documents including a notebook containing a travel itinerary.
  - Miscellaneous Biographical Documents, 1926-1975 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Certificates, 1920-1967 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Oversized material housed in OV 7.
  - Teaching Files, 1935-1952 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Medals, 1919-1967 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Oversized Certificate, 1957 (Box OV 7)
    Oversized material from Box 1, Folder 2.
- Correspondence, 1929-circa 1975; Series 2; 0.4 Linear feet Box 1, OV 7
  Arrangement note
  This series is arranged into 4 subseries.
  Correspondence with friends and colleagues has been arrange chronologically. Lettes from individuals who had correspondence with Kaplan of three letters or less are found within the "Friends and Colleagues" folders. Correspondence with galleries, museums, and associations has been arranged alphabetically. Letters from individuals who had correspondence with Kaplan of three letters or less are found within the "Galleries, Museums, and Associations" folders.
  2.1 Family Correspondence, 1957-1976
  2.2 Correspondence with Friends and Colleagues, circa 1930-1975
  2.3 Correspondence with Galleries, Museums, and Associations, 1932-1977
  2.4 Christmas and Greeting Cards, 1952-1962
  This series consists mainly of incoming letters. A smaller amount of replies and outgoing letters are included.
  The majority of the family correspondence is from Kaplan to his wife Virginia while he was traveling in 1957 and 1960. Also found is a letter written upon Kaplan's death to Virginia. The remaining family letters are from Abraham Kaplan and Helen Tumin. A few of the letters from Abraham Kaplan are in Yiddish.
  Correspondence from universities and colleges, galleries, museums, and other art organizations and institutions documents Kaplan's business affairs. Letters discuss exhibitions, loans and sales of artwork, and the Works Progress Administration.
  Correspondence with friends and colleagues include Aya Ishigaki, Sol Wilson, Louis Lozowick, Adolph Gottlieb, Chaim Gross, and Raphael Soyer. These letters document news of friends and activities and political organizations of interest to Kaplan.
  The majority of the christmas and greeting cards are undated but include cards from Milton Avery, Chaim Gross, Aya Ishigaki, and Sol and Dora Wilson. Many of the cards are illustrated.
  - Family Correspondence, 1957-1976; 2.1
    - Abraham Kaplan, 1965; 1970; 1967 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Helen Tumin, 1975-1976 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Joseph Kaplan to Virginia Kaplan, 1957; circa 1975; 1960 (Box 1, Folder 6-8)
  - Correspondence with Friends and Colleagues, 1940-1975; 2.2
    - Ishigaki, Aya, 1959; 1958; 1946 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Lozowick, Louis, 1930-1946 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Wilson, Sol, 1936; 1934 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Friends and Colleagues, 1929-1975 (Box 1, Folder 12-14)
    - Friends and Colleagues, circa 1930-circa 1970 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence with Galleries, Museums, and Associations, 1940- 1975; 2.3
    - American Federation of Arts, 1958; 1956 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Artists Equity Association, 1949-1961 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Artist for Victory, Inc., 1944 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Audubon Artists, inc., 1954-1966 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Berhardt Crystal Galleries, Inc., 1962 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Butler Institute of American Art, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Cape Cod Art Association, 1965; 1960; 1964 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Carnegie Institute, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Chapelbrook Foundation, 1968; 1967 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - College of Fine Arts and Applied Arts University of Illinois, 1949; 1952 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Commonwealth of Massachusetts, 1962; 1961 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Connecticut Watercolor Society, Inc., 1962 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Corcoran Gallery of Art, 1955; 1956 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Crotty, Frank, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Department of Information, The Federal Art Project, 1938; 1937 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Everson Museum of Art, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Federal Support for the Visual Arts: The New Deal and Now, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Galleries, Museums, and Associations, 1932-1977 (Box 1, Folder 33-34)
    - Grand Central Art Galleries, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - John Reed Club, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - National Academy of Design, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Pennsylvania Academy of the Fine Arts, 1947; 1946 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Small, Warren, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - United States Treasury Department, 1935-1937 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Who's Who, 1952-1962 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Christmas and Greeting Cards, 1952-1963; 2.4
    - Christmas and Greeting Cards, 1952-1963 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Oversized Illustrated Greeting from Lerner Family, undated (Box OV 7)
      Oversized material from Box 1, Folder 42.
- Personal Business Records, circa 1920-1977; Series 3; 0.2 Linear feet Box 1
  Kaplan's art-related financial material includes WPA records, a list of artwork, price lists, loan and sale records, and exhibition notification cards. Some of the series consists of routine transactions not necessarily related to Kaplan's work including bank records, an address list, and income and expense reports.
  - List of Works of Art, circa 1920-circa 1975 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Price Lists, 1962-1975 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Artwork Loans and Sale Records, 1955-1977 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Exhibition Notification Cards, 1949-1964 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Financial Records, 1957-1974 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Earning and Expense Reports, 1963-1971 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - United States Works Progress Administration, 1935-1937 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Contract, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Address List, circa 1940 (Box 1, Folder 51)
- Printed Material, 1915-1975; Series 4; 2.3 Linear feet Box 1, 2, 3, OV 7
  Printed Material includes exhibition catalogs for Kaplan exhibitions dating from 1924-1971. A large portion of this series also consists of newspaper clippings and a few magazine clippings documenting exclusively Kaplan's exhibitions. Also found are magazines and copies of his commercial artwork, exhibition announcements and publications.
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1924-1950 (Box 1, Folder 52-57)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, circa 1940-1976 (Box 2, Folder 1-17)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1924-circa 1975 (Box 3, Folder 1-4)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, Other Artists, 1921-1966 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Invitations, circa 1947 - 1975 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Clippings, 1936-1975 (Box 3, Folder 7-18)
  - Clipping Scrapbook, 1925-1952 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Clipping Scrapbook, 1952-1955 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Commerical Artwork by Kaplan, circa 1930-circa 1950 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - American Artist School Program, 1936-1939 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - The Left Journal, 1931 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Partisan Review Journal, 1934-1935 (Box 3, Folder 24-25)
  - Experimental Cinema Magazine, 1931 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - The Miscellany Magazine, 1931 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - U.S. Camera Magazine, 1940 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Reprint from New York Sun and New York Herald, 1915-1922 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Program for James Joyce's Ulysses in Nighttown, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Manuel of Classical Erotology Typescript, undated (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Material, 1937; circa 1930-circa 1950 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Oversized Commerical Artwork by Kaplan, Page Proofs, circa 1930 (Box OV 7)
    Oversized material from Box 3, Folder 21.
- Artwork, circa 1940-circa 1960; Series 5; 2 Folders Box 3, 5
  Artwork includes four etchings by Kaplan, three of which are metal plates and one a linoleum block. Also included are a few undated pencil and pen sketches on the back of exhibition material by an unidentified artist.
  - Sketches, undated (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Etchings, undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Photographic Material, 1917-circa 1975; Series 6; 1.3 Linear feet Box 4, 6, OV 7
  Found here are personal photographs, photographs taken by Kaplan, photographs of artwork, and miscellaneous photographs. Personal photographs depict mostly family and friends. Portraits of friends include Eitaro and Aya Ishigaki, Chaim Gross, Raphael Soyer, William Gropper, and Joseph De Martini. There is a large amount of unidentified and undated photogarphs of couples and groups, men, women, and children. Photographs taken by Kaplan include artists demonstrations in the 30s, New York City, family, friends, and travel slides of Haiti, Trindad, Mexico, Captiva, and Sanibel.
  This series is arranged in 3 subseries
  6.1 Personal Photographs, 1921-circa 1975
  6.2 Photographs taken by Kaplan, circa 1932-circa 1960
  6.3 Photographic Material of Artwork, circa 1930-circa 1975
  - Personal Photographs, 1921-circa 1975; 6.1
    - Joseph Kaplan, 1921-circa 1975 (Box 4, Folder 1-5)
    - Virginia Kaplan, circa 1917-circa 1975 (Box 4, Folder 6-8)
    - Joseph and Virginia Kaplan, circa 1927-circa 1975 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Virginia Kaplan's Photograph Albums, 1917-circa 1927 (Box 4, Folder 10-16)
    - Joseph Kaplan's Mother, undated (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Family and Friends, circa 1940-circa 1960 (Box 4, Folder 18-23)
    - Unidentified Couples and Groups, circa 1940-circa 1960 (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - Unidentified Men, circa 1940-circa 1960 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - Unidentified Women, circa 1940-circa 1960 (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - Unidentified Children, circa 1940-circa 1960 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Photographs Taken by Kaplan, circa 1932-circa 1960; 6.2
    - Century of Progress, circa 1933-circa 1934 (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - Demonstrations, 1934 (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - East Broadway Park, undated (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - Friends, 1940 (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Groppen House, undated (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Liberty Group, circa 1950-circa 1960 (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - May Day, 1934-1935 (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - Radio City Theatre, undated (Box 4, Folder 35)
    - Washington Square Park Exhibition, circa 1932-circa 1957 (Box 4, Folder 36)
    - Miscellaneous Photographs, undated (Box 4, Folder 37)
    - Miscellaneous Negatives, undated (Box 4, Folder 38)
    - Slides of Family, Friends, and Cats, circa 1940-circa 1960 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Slides of Travel, 1956-1957 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Photographic Material of Artwork, circa 1930-circa 1975; 6.3
    - Photographs of Artwork, circa 1930-circa 1975 (Box 4, Folder 39)
    - Negatives of Artwork, circa 1930-circa 1975 (Box 4, Folder 40-41)
    - Glass Transparencies of Artwork, circa 1930-circa 1975 (Box 4, Folder 42)
    - Photographs of Commercial Artwork, circa 1930-circa 1975 (Box 4, Folder 43)
    - Slides of Artwork, circa 1930-circa 1975 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Oversized Photographs of Commerical Artwork, circa 1930 (Box OV 7)
      Oversized material from Box 4, Folder 43.